Guide to the Henry Barnard Papers 1765-1935 (Bulk 1830-1899) MSS.033
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Series IV: Printed Material
  Series IV contains seven folders of printed matter, many of which are brief articles cut from a variety of books and periodicals. Most concern Barnard's life and projects, or merely mention him, while others are simply advertisements, such as catalogs of Barnard's publications and advertisements for the American Journal of Education. Present as well are a few printed greeted cards and invitations to ceremonies and professional gatherings. Some of the items are annotated but only a few substantially. A small number of documents in this series may have been part of the correspondence file at one time for they bear index numbers.
  - Clippings, Pamphlets, and Announcements, 1850-1881, (Bulk: 1850-1869) (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Includes "An Inaugural Address Delivered in the Senate Chamber of the Capitol before the Board of Regents of the [Wisconsin] State University" by E.S. Carr, 1856, January 16; "Barnard's Educational Labors," unknown author/source [1858]; "Circular" advertising Barnard's American Journal of Education by Thomas W. Bicknell, 1881; Photocopied newspaper article "Professor Henry Barnard," from The Daily Crescent, New Orleans, 1851, June 10, (index number 2-2787); Photocopy of newspaper article "Honorable Henry Barnard" by Lydia H. Sigourney, 1854, September (index number 2-3574); 3 "Notices" regarding special meetings of the Board of Trustees at Watkinson Library, 1863; 2 copies of an announcement for the Annual Meeting of the National Teacher's Association by W.E. Sheldon, 1863, June 20, with handwritten notes on the reverse of both; 2 further "Notices" from the Watkinson Library, also 1863; Printed message from John Eaton, Jr., 1868, Sept. 16; Incomplete "Report of Committee on Education and Labor to the House of Representatives," by S.F. Cary, 1869, February 16.
  - Clippings and Advertisements, 1870-1879 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Includes: "Education in District of Columbia: Letter of Commissioner of Education," by Henry Barnard, 1870, January 19; Title pages and table of contents from the American Journal of Education, vol. 9 of the National Series (vol. 24 of the entire series), 1874-5; "Centenniel Growth in Nationality, Industries, and Education," unknown author, 1876, July 4; "Retrospect and Prospect-1878," extracts from letters exchanged by R.H. Quick and Henry Barnard printed in the American Journal of Education, 1878; "Paris Exposition, 1878, Award of Gold and Silver Medals," unknown author/ source; 2 advertisements for "Barnard's American Journal of Education," unknown authors, 1878; "Program of Exercises for the Meeting of the National Educational Association to be Held at Philadelphia, July 29, 30, and 31, 1879," unknown author.
  - Clippings and Advertisements, 1880-1889 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Includes multiple copies of "Circular" advertising the American Journal of Education, by Thomas Bicknell, 1881; "Henry Barnard in Connecticut" by Thomas Bicknell, 1881, with "Henry Barnard- The American Educator" by John D. Philbrick, from the Massachusetts Teacher, 1858, appended; "Connecticut Schools and Education," by John W. Stedman, 1881; "Barnard's Encyclopedia of Education, Appeal by Miss Peabody," by Elizabeth P. Peabody, [1881]; "From the Record of the Class of 1830," [W.R. Cone], [1885]; "Connecticut Schools and Educators, Letter from Henry Barnard" by Henry Barnard, 1886; "Folk Lore Publication Society," by William Wells Newell, 1887; "American Library of Education and Schools," by Henry Barnard, 1887; Portion of a publication sent to Henry Barnard by R. H. Quick, 1889; "Rev. A.D. Mayo's Ministry of Education in the South", with testimonials from John Eaton, N.H.R. Dawson, J.L.M. Curry, William T. Harris, Atticus G. Haywood, 1889.
  - Clippings, 1890-1987 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Includes "Henry Barnard: the Nestor of American Education" by James L. Hughes (index number: 11421); "Table of Contents" from Pestalozzi and Swiss Pedagogy by Henry Barnard;Circuit Rider of the American Schools: Albert Edward Winship by George P. Winship; Printed card (index number 11729); An advertisement for the Lyceum Theatre's production of "Nathan Hale" ca. 1899 (index number: 11719); Advertisement for [D]evil's Island ca. 1899 (index number: 11720); printed page, origin unknown, describing two recognitions of Barnard in education literature of 1890 (index number 11716); and subscription offer for a "A Weekly Library for 5 Cents a Week" (index number: 11732).
  - Clippings, 1899, Undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Includes "Instruction by Correspondence," by E.F. Ware, undated; "Index" from Reminiscences by John Hooker, 1899; Photocopy of printed version of a letter to Henry Barnard from Earl Barnes; "University of Cambridge," unknown author, undated; "The Co-Operation of Parents Solicited by the Teacher of Their Children," from Educational Tracts No. 9, unknown author, undated; "Whittier and the New England Review," by S.T.P., undated; "Essentials," by W.W. Stetson, undated; "Circular of the Board of Normal School Regents of the State of Wisconsin," unknown author, undated; "To the Teachers and Controllers of Public Schools," by Grigg, Elliot, and Co., undated; "Prospectus of the National Society of Literature and Science," Unknown author, undated; Extract from "A Brief History of the Rhode Island Institute of Instruction, from 1844 to 1874," by Edwin M. Stone, undated; Typescript summary of a survey published in "Revue de l'Instruction Publique" by Alphonse LeRoy, unknown author, undated; Photocopies of newspaper articles regarding Henry Barnard; "The Practical Spelling Book," by T.H. Gallaudet and Horace Hooker, undated; "Dr. Henry Barnard's Standard Educational Publications," unknown author, undated; "Table of Contents" for Christianity in Education, Edited by Henry Barnard (index number: 1077); "Sur le Sentiment de l'honnete dans les Enfants" by Luigi Anfosso, undated; "Abstract of a Paper on the Psychic Unit," by William S. Wadsworth, undated; "Influence de l'age des Parents sur les Caracteres Psycho-Physiques des Enfants," by Antoine Marro, undated; "Die Sprache des Kindes und der Naturvolker," by H. Gutzmann, undated; "Mr. Tefft's Remarks," undated (index number: 11740); "The Quarterly Register of Current History," by The Evening News Association, undated (index number: 11741).
  - Certificates for Gifts, 1853, 1863, [1897] (Box 9, Folder 6)
    From Brown University Library, 1853 (Index number: 3344); The Public Library of the City of Boston, 1863; and an official Birthday Greeting from the University of Wisconsin-Madison, from C.K. Adams, [1897].
  - Clippings, [1888], 1896, 1897, 1899, Undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Includes photocopy of "Henry Barnard," by Albert E. Winship, from Christian Register, 1896; photocopy of "The Barnard Celebration," by Will S. Monroe, undated; Photocopy of "In Dr. Barnard's Honor," unknown author, from the Yale Alumni Weekly, 1897; Photocopy of newspaper article "Henry Barnard," unknown author, 1896; Photocopy of newspaper article "The Founder of Schools," unknown author, 1899; Photocopy of newspaper article "Barnard, Henry," unknown author, 1888.
- Series V: Letters in Other Collections
  Series V contains five folders of photo-static copies made from letters written by Henry Barnard to Lyman C. Draper, J.H. Armsby, and Ashbel Smith. The originals of the typescript items in the first folder belong to the Wisconsin State Historical Society. The originals for the photo-static copies in folders 2 through 5 belong to the Ashbel Smith Papers collection at the University of Texas.
  - Wisconsin Historical Society, letters from Henry Barnard to Lyman C. Draper and J.H. Armsby, 1856-1858 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - From the Ashbel Smith Papers, University of Texas (Photostatic), 1829-1833 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - From the Ashbel Smith Papers, University of Texas (Photostatic), 1834-1837 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - From the Ashbel Smith Papers, University of Texas (Photostatic), 1839-1849 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - From the Ashbel Smith Papers, University of Texas (Photostatic), 1855-1860; 1881-1882 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Series VI: Addenda
  Series VI retains typescript versions of missives, often from the 1840s and 1850s, that Henry Barnard selected to be copied. The transcripts were made by Will Monroe in his capacity as Henry Barnard's assistant, and some include items, often newspaper clippings, that may have been enclosed with the original letters. Also included are a few letters addressed to and written by Will Monroe as well as typescript biographical sketches and handwritten notes regarding people, locations, and events relevant to Barnard's life in particular and the subject of education in general.
  - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1823-1836 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1838-1839 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1840-1841 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1842-1843 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1844-1845 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1846-1848 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1849-1852 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1853-1855 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1856-1859 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1860-1869 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1870-1879 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1880-1889 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1890-1896 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard, 1897-1899 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Monroe Notes on Henry Barnard and Monroe's Correspondence, 1900-1935, Undated (Box 10, Folder 15)
    Includes items stamped with alphabetical index numbers 11754, 11747, 11746
- Series VII: Photograph File
  Series VII holds forty-nine folders containing largely undated images displaying correspondents and contemporaries of Henry Barnard. They appear in a variety of printed formats including cabinet photographs, lithographs, and engravings which have been installed on cardboard mounts. The last folder contains photocopies of images from the first three folders in the series. At least some of the documents in this series once belonged to Will Monroe.
  - A-Bar, Undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Barnard, Henry, 1883, 1893, Undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Barnes-Bz, Undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Ca-Ch, Undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Ci-Coo, Undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - D-Di, Undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Dickinson, John W., Undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Dj-Dz, Undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - E, Undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - F, Undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - G-Gn, Undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Go-Gz, Undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - H-Ham, Undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Han-Haz, Undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Hb-Hn, Undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Ho-Hos, Undated (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Hot-Hu, Undated (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Hughes, Ada; Hughes, James, Undated (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Huh-Hz, Undated (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - I-J, Undated (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - K-Ki, Undated (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Kj-Kz, Undated (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - L-Li, Undated (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Lj-Lz, Undated (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - M-Maq, Undated (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Mar, Undated (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Mas-Mel, Undated (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - Meleney, Clarence, Undated (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - Mem-Mez, Undated (Box 12, Folder 30)
  - Mf-Mow, Undated (Box 12, Folder 31)
  - Mowry, Dr. William A., Undated (Box 12, Folder 32)
  - Mox-Mz, Undated (Box 12, Folder 33)
  - N, Undated (Box 12, Folder 34)
  - O, Undated (Box 12, Folder 35)
  - P-Pe, Undated (Box 12, Folder 36)
  - Pf-Pz, Undated (Box 12, Folder 37)
  - Q, Undated (Box 12, Folder 38)
  - R, Undated (Box 12, Folder 39)
  - S-Se, Undated (Box 12, Folder 40)
  - Sf-Sk, Undated (Box 12, Folder 41)
  - Sm-Sz, Undated (Box 12, Folder 42)
  - T, Undated (Box 12, Folder 43)
  - U, Undated (Box 12, Folder 44)
  - V, Undated (Box 12, Folder 45)
  - W-Wh, Undated (Box 12, Folder 46)
  - Wi-Wz, Undated (Box 12, Folder 47)
  - Y-Z; Miscellaneous photograph of Henry Barnard's home, Undated (Box 12, Folder 48)
  - Photocopies A-B, Undated (Box 12, Folder 49)
  - Cop-Cz, Undated (Box 11, Folder 6)